旧金山国际机场 临近午夜
It is almost midnight at San Francisco International Airport
加拿大航空759号班机正在进近中
as Air Canada Flight 759 is approaching.
这趟落地轻松拿下后 飞行员们就可以休息了
Just one more easy landing, and the pilots can call it a day.
但他们没有发现今天的机场看起来与以往有所不同
What they are not aware of is that the airport looks quite a bit different than usual.
他们获准落地跑道28R 就在28L跑道的旁边
They are clear to land on runway 28R, located next to 28L.
但由于跑道维护
However, due to maintenance,
28L跑道当晚处于关闭状态 灯光也熄灭了
the runway 28L is closed that night, and the lights had been turned off.
而两位飞行员都曾飞过这个机场
But as the pilots who both have landed at this airport before
他们都以为会看到两条平行的跑道
were expecting to see two parallel runways,
所以他们错把中间的跑道认成了28L
they make a mistake, thinking that the center runway is 28L,
把右侧的滑行道当成了28R跑道
they confuse the taxi way on the right to be runway 28R.
而在那条滑行道上 有四架飞机正排好队准备离场
On that very taxi way, four other flights are lined up for departure.
美联航1号班机 机型波音787
United One, a Boeing 787;
菲律宾航空115号班机 机型空客A340
Philippine Airlines 115, an Airbus 340;
后面还是两架美联航
and two more United flights.
四架飞机总共超过1000名乘客
In total over 1,000 passengers,
而加拿大航空的飞机正径直朝他们飞去
and the Air Canada flight is heading straight towards them all.
跑道关闭的消息是列在航行通告(NOTAM)上的
The information about the runway closure was listed in a so-called NOTAM.
NOTAM直译"给飞行员的通知" 会列出所有飞行相关的特殊细节
These are NOtices To AirMen which summarize any exceptional details regarding the flight.
但这些通知又臭又长 通常有好几页
But these lists are quite long, typically several pages,
其实很难能从中找到真正和飞行有关联的细节
and it's not easy to pick out the details that are actually relevant for the flight.
机组没注意到跑道关闭的通知
The flight crew missed the runway closure.
飞行员获准的进近方式为"目视进近"
The pilots had been cleared for a so-called visual approach.
即他们可以根据肉眼所见来操控飞机对准跑道
This means that they can line up with the runway manually, steering the aircraft according to what they see.
当晚气象情况较好 目视进近属于正常的程序
Considering the clear weather conditions, the visual approach is the normal procedure.
但由于之前发生过飞机落错跑道甚至落在滑行道上的事件
But as landings on false runways or even taxiways have occurred before,
所以细心一点的飞行员通常会用仪表进近作为备份
careful pilots usually back up their approach with instrument guidance.
本案例中 飞行员本来可以使用28R跑道的仪表着陆系统(ILS)
In this case, they could have used the instrument landing system, ILS for short, of runway 28R
来确认自己的航迹是否正确
to confirm that they really were on the right path.
想要激活这个系统
In order to activate this system,
飞行员需要把跑道ILS对应的频率输入到导航的接收机中
a frequency corresponding to that runway has to be dialed into the navigation receiver.
现代的飞行管理计算机通常能自动完成此项内容
Modern flight management computers usually do this automatically,
但在本案例中 这个频率需要手动输入
but in this case, it had to be dialed in manually,
且出于某种原因 副驾并没有完成该操作
and for some reason the first officer didn't do that.
机组当时已经飞一整天了
The cockpit crew has had a long day.
他们从加拿大多伦多起飞 此时已是他们生物钟的凌晨三点了
Coming from Toronto, Canada, their inner clock is already at three past midnight,
过度自信与疲劳导致了犯错
and overconfidence and fatigue have been attributed to these mistakes.
加拿大飞行员的疲劳管理规定比美国的规定松
Canadian pilot fatigue rules were less stringent than US regulations,
该航班的机长在过去19小时内都没有足够的休息时间
and the flight's captain had no significant rest period for the last 19 hours.
此时还没人发现飞机正对准滑行道
As no one recognized that the airplane is lined up for the taxiway,
加拿大航空正一步步走向一场灾难
Air Canada heads closer and closer to disaster.
该机场28R跑道目视进近的理想航迹比跑道方向稍稍偏右
The ideal flight path for the visual approach at this airport
comes in at a slight angle from the right.
目的是让进场的飞机尽量离西岸远一点 减少噪音污染
This was done in order to have incoming planes stay further away from the west shore of the bay,
reducing noise pollution.
因此 从塔台视角看 飞机相对跑道中线稍稍偏左是很正常的
Therefore, it is not unusual that from the tower perspective
airplanes appear a little offset to the left of the runway center line.
此时加拿大航空离跑道越来越近 就快要撞上等待的几架飞机了
Air Canada further closes in on the runway, about to crash into the parked planes.
他们也发现了一些异常 于是确认了一下
And as they notice that something seems off, they reassure themselves.
此时 塔台的语音记录显示塔台管制员花了大约五秒才回复这个问题
At this moment, the tower voice recording
shows that it took the tower controller about five seconds to answer the call.
当晚只有一位管制员在值班
There was only one controller managing the traffic at this time.
通常还会有一位地面管制员负责地面交通
Normally, an additional ground controller is responsible for handling the ground traffic,
但在不那么繁忙的夜间时段 塔台管制员通常会同时负责两个频率
but during the less busy night hours, the tower controller often works both frequencies.
美联航1号班机的飞行员在C滑行道的首位等待时
The pilots of United Flight One, waiting as first in line on taxiway Charlie
也听到了刚刚加航与空管的对话
were listening in on this exchange with Air Canada.
他们可能还奇怪为什么加航相对跑道中线还是如此偏左
They probably were wondering why Air Canada was still so far to the left of the center line.
当他们最后确认飞行正对准滑行道降落的时候
When it became obvious to them that the plane was heading for the taxiway,
他们立即在无线电中报告 甚至为了节省时间都没提自己的呼号
they spoke up quickly, not even mentioning their own call sign in order to save any second.
我们刚刚目睹的事件 可能成为航空界有史以来最大的事故
What we just witnessed could have been the largest accident in general aviation that ever happened.
加航759离排队等待的飞机的尾翼最近只有几米
Air Canada 759 missed the tail fins of the waiting aircraft only by a few meters.
这段事件的真实影像记录了当时飞机离得有多近
This real footage of the incident shows just how close the planes were.
事后局方启动了调查
A full investigation was launched,
美国国家运输安全委员会(NTSB)给出了完整的改进建议
and the National Transportation Safety Board has released an entire list of recommendations,
其中很多都已经实施
many of which have already been implemented.
旧金山机场不再允许当相邻跑道关闭时在夜间进行目视进近
Visual approaches at night are no longer allowed at San Francisco when an adjacent runway is closed.
另外 在夜间进港高峰结束前 需要两名管制员在岗
Furthermore, two air traffic controllers are now required to be on duty until the late night arrival rush is over.
该事件提醒了人们 机场沟通不畅有多危险
The incident became a striking reminder of the dangers of miscommunications at airports,
但人们是否从中吸取了足够教训 就越来越难说了
but whether enough lessons have really been learned is increasingly being put into question,
因为今年在美国机场发生了大量跑道侵入的事件
as this year saw an unprecedented amount of close calls at US airports.
"纽约肯尼迪机场两架飞机的一次跑道侵入事故征候正在接受联邦调查"
"A close call between two planes at New York's JFK Airport is now under federal investigation."
"在奥斯汀 一场机场危机被即使化解"
"In Austin, an airport crisis caught just in time."
"本周三 伯班克机场发生了今年第四起跑道侵入事件"
"This fourth close call of the year happened at Burbank Airport on Wednesday."
"今晚 美国联邦航空局已经对另一起两架飞机差点相撞的事件展开调查"
"Well, tonight the FAA has launched an investigation into yet another near collision of two aircraft."
"这一次发生在波士顿洛根国际机场"
"This one at Boston Logan International Airport."
"今早 两架飞机的另一次跑道侵入事件正在接受调查"
"This morning, another close call between two planes is under investigation."
"美国联邦航空局表示 共和航空的一架飞机在里根国家机场穿越了错误的跑道"
"The FAA says a Republic Airways flight crossed the wrong runway at Reagan National Airport."
2023年1月13日 两架飞机在纽约肯尼迪机场差点相撞
On January 13th, 2023, two airplanes almost crashed into each other at JFK Airport in New York City.
美国航空106号班机沿B滑行道从西北方向驶来
American Airlines Flight 106 was coming from the northwest along Taxiway Bravo.
为了滑行至离场跑道04L起飞
To get to the departure end of runway 04L where they were gonna take off,
管制员通知他们沿B滑行道滑行 右转进入K滑行道
they were told to taxi along Bravo and then turn onto Kilo.
注意 飞行员并没有复诵他们的起飞跑道 只复诵了滑行路线
Note that the pilot did not read back the runway assignment but just the taxi route.
这与规章稍有不符 但管制员并没有注意到
This is a minor deviation from protocol, and the controller simply dismissed it,
而这埋下了危险的种子
something that will prove dangerous.
在他们快到转弯点的时候
At about the same time as they reached that intersection,
达美航空1943号班机在04L跑道准备起飞 已获起飞许可
Delta Airlines flight 1943 was ready for takeoff on runway 04L and received its final clearance.
同时 美航106继续滑行 管制员通知其在K滑行道右转
Meanwhile, American Airlines 106 is continuing to taxi, and is instructed to turn at Kilo
但他们并没有右转进入K滑行道 而是直行进入J滑行道
But instead of turning right onto Kilo, they taxi straight ahead onto Juliet,
并穿越了达美正在用于离场的跑道
thereby crossing the very same runway on which the Delta flight is departing.
美航的飞行员为何继续向前滑行 目前尚不清楚
Why the pilots of the American Airlines flight continue taxiing straight ahead is unclear.
肯尼迪机场的确经常使用31L跑道离场
JFK does often operate departures on runway 31L.
可能飞行员太习惯走那条滑行路线了
Perhaps the pilots were so used to that taxi route
他们脑中以为自己要从31L跑道起飞
that in their mind they were going to take off from there.
导致他们先入为主认为自己要从31L跑道离场的另一因素是
Another factor that might have pre-programmed them to believe they were departing from 31L
当前机场风向340 18节 阵风24节
was that the current winds were 340 degrees with 18 knots and gusts of 24 knots.
这样的气象条件有利于31L跑道的离场
These conditions would have favored runway 31L for departure.
但由于机场运行原因 他们使用了04L跑道用于离场
For operational reasons, however, the airport was using runway 04L for departure.
另外值得注意的是 两架飞机飞行员互相听不到对方
Also noteworthy is that both flight crews could not hear each other.
美航106用的地面频率 达美1943用的塔台频率
American 106 was on the ground frequency, while Delta 1943 was on the tower frequency.
他们各自和不同的管制员交流
They were talking to different controllers
脑中并没有另一边在干什么的画面
and did not have a mental picture of what the other one was doing.
好在错误发生后仅几秒钟
Thankfully, just seconds after the mistake,
塔台管制员发现了异常 并果断做出反应
the tower controller notices what's happening and reacts extremely well.
约300米
达美的飞机在跑道与J滑行道交叉点前约1000英尺处停了下来
The Delta plane comes to a stop about 1000 feet shy of intersection Juliet,
无人伤亡
and nobody was injured.
美国联邦航空管理局按类型与严重程度将跑道侵入分类
The US Federal Aviation Administration categorizes runway incursions by type and severity.
事故: 跑道侵入导致了碰撞的发生
A类: 勉强了避免碰撞的严重事故征候
B类: 间隔缩小至存在显著碰撞的可能 只有在关键时刻采取纠正或避让措施 才能避免碰撞发生的事故征候
C类: 有充足时间和(或)距离采取措施避免碰撞发生的事故征候
D类: 符合跑道侵入的定义 如指定供航空器起降的地面保护区内错误出现车辆/人/航空器 但不会立即产生安全后果的跑道侵入
除了真正造成事故的跑道侵入事件
Besides the incursions that actually result in an accident,
一共四种类型 从"勉强避免碰撞发生的跑道侵入的严重事故征候"
there are four categories ranging from close calls in which a collision was just narrowly avoided
到"符合跑道侵入定义但不会立即产生安全后果"
to errors that at no point posed any security risks.
肯尼迪机场这次的严重程度被归为B类
The JFK incident was serious enough to be categorized as Category B.
从数据上看
Looking at the statistics,
过去20年的严重事故征候发生次数有下降趋势
it can be observed that the number of serious incidents over the past two decades has been going down.
2007年发生了22起A类跑道侵入
While there were 22 category A incidents in 2007,
而过去十年发生次数从未超过9起
there have never been more than 9 such incidents per year in the past decade.
B类跑道侵入也同样呈现下降趋势
As far as category B incursions are concerned, a similar trend is visible.
如果观察过去十来年的数据
If you look at the last decade or so,
会发现每年通常有10到20次这样的事故征候
you would see between 10 and 20 times a year typically that this would happen.
而今年我们可能会超过20次
This year we're on track to have more than 20,
其中任何一次都是我们不想看到的
and even one is one that I would not like to see happen.
肯尼迪机场的事件让媒体对机场安全产生了很大关注
The JFK incident has put a large media spotlight on airport safety,
但仅仅过去三周 另一起跑道侵入就发生了
but still it will just take three weeks until the next close call,
这次可能是最可怕的
this one perhaps the most scary one.
联邦快递1432号货运班机 机型波音767货机 从孟菲斯起飞
Flight FedEx 1432, a Boeing 767 cargo plane, was coming from Memphis
在当地时间清晨抵达奥斯汀
and arrived in the early morning hours in Austin.
奥斯汀在这个时段 通常地面会有一层厚度不高的雾
As happens so often in Austin, the ground is covered with a thin layer of fog,
只有大约一千英尺厚 但非常浓
just about a thousand feet thick, but very dense.
机组当前高度还在浓雾上方 享受晴好的天气
They are still high above that fog layer enjoying a clear sky,
但他们需要扎进浓雾中才能降落
but they will have to dive through it for their landing.
由于低能见 联邦快递1432需要执行所谓的"三类仪表进近方式"
Due to the low visibility,
FedEx 1432 had to execute what is called a category three instrument approach,
该程序用于超低能见与云底高度几乎接近地面的气象条件
a procedure applied at very low visibility and clouds reaching almost to the ground.
这种进近方式会激活飞机的自动着陆系统
For such approaches, the auto land system of the airplane is used,
机组只需监控一切系统的正常运行即可
and the flight crew only monitors the correct operations of all systems.
这些都是机组的常规操作流程 没什么稀罕的
This in itself is just routine for the flight crew and nothing unusual.
塔台提供的跑道视程(RVR)告知了跑道三个不同位置的能见度 单位英尺
The RVR value given by the tower controller denotes the visibility in feet at three different points along the runway,
三个位置为接地段 中间段 停止段
near the touchdown point, the middle, and the end.
刚刚机组提到的"过5.4" 指他们离ILS发射机5.4英里
ILS的航向信标台位于沿着陆跑道中心延长线
跑道末端距离一般为250-400米
距跑道入口最小距离为2200米 最大不宜超过4000米
ILS的下滑信标台位于着陆跑道接地区的任意一侧
距跑道入口距离按照有关国家标准计算 通常为200-400米 与跑道中心线的距离为75-200米通常为120米
The phrase passing 5.4 means that they are 5.4 miles away from the ILS transmitter,
ILS发射机位于跑道末端
which sits at the end of the runway.
与此同时 西南航空708号班机呼叫
At just this moment, Southwest 708 calls in.
塔台管制的意图是让西南航在联邦快递落地前使用相同的跑道起飞
The tower controller's intention
is to have the Southwest flight take off on the same runway before the FedEx lands.
三英里间隔通常还不错 可以让离场飞机插队起飞
Three miles is usually a comfortable spacing to let a departure slip in front,
塔台告知"五边三英里有交通 767重型"
and the phrase "traffic on three mile final is a heavy 767"
是想提醒西南航机组 联邦快递的飞机快落地了 请快速离场
is to inform the Southwest crew about the incoming FedEx plane which requires them to do a speedy departure,
但他们起飞好像花得比平常要久
but things take longer than expected.
此时联邦快递已经扎进浓雾
Time is ticking as the FedEx is entering the fog layer
驾驶舱外什么也看不见了
not able to see anything out of their cockpit windows anymore.
他们与跑道的距离缩短到了1.2英里
Their distance to the runway has now shrunk to merely 1.2 miles,
他们开始担心西南航还停在跑道上
and they are becoming nervous about the Southwest still sitting on the runway
塔台给西南708起飞许可已经过去了60秒
60 seconds have now passed since the tower gave Southwest 708 the take off clearance,
他们显然还停在跑道入口
and apparently they are still standing at the threshold.
虽然准备起飞滑跑没有一个硬性的限制时间
Although there is no fixed time limit for starting the takeoff roll,
但塔台肯定希望飞行员能尽快起飞
it is expected that pilots perform the takeoff in an expeditious way.
与此同时 联邦快递正在浓雾中下降高度
Meanwhile, FedEx is descending through the fog layer
紧盯慢慢浮现的引进灯光
and highly concentrated to look for the approach lights that show up.
离地150尺时 浓雾稍稍散去
At about 150 feet above the ground, the fog clears up a bit,
他们看到了西南708的灯光 发现其仍在滑跑 速度还很慢
and they can make out the lights of Southwest 708 still on the runway rolling, but yet very slow.
机组迅速执行复飞 并且直接向西南航机组发指令:
They immediately initiate a go around, and they address the Southwest crew directly.
塔台说这句话因为他们误以为上一条消息是西南航发的
The tower's transmission is the result of a misunderstanding
as he assumed the abort message had come from Southwest
塔台以为西南航通报自己中断了起飞
which was informing them about aborting their takeoff run.
西南航的机组此时速度可能已经超过了V1
The Southwest crew, however, was probably already beyond their V1 speed,
此时中断起飞会有危险
and rejecting the takeoff would've been dangerous.
此时机组无心解释 所以只是回答"不同意"
As they were busy, they simply answered "negative".
这段对话显示了短时间内事情可以变得有多乱
This exchange shows just how confusing things can get very quickly.
两架飞机最近距离小于100英尺
Both planes come within 100 feet of each other,
而联邦快递成功爬升飞离西南航的飞机
but the FedEx is able to out climb the departing Southwest plane.
通常 一架飞机是不允许直接给另一架飞机下达指令的
Normally, one aircraft is not allowed to give instructions to another.
而联邦快递机组却这样做了 显示出当前情况的紧急
The fact that the FedEx crew did shows the severity of the situation.
当塔台后来搞清楚发生了什么后
After the tower controller got things sorted out,
他又重新接管控制 下指令让两架飞机各自飞离
he takes active control again and gives instructions to both airplanes that keep them separated.
两架飞机当时本不应该如此接近
Two airplanes should never come this close in such a situation.
同时 几个事件的顺序也表明 有几个程序的确起到了避免相撞的作用
At the same time, the sequence of events also shows that several procedures did work in avoiding a collision.
无论是直接看到了跑道上的西南航 还是TCAS系统的警告
Whether by directly seeing the Southwest on the runway or a warning of the TCAS system
联邦快递机组都及时采取了行动 与另一架飞机保持了距离
the FedEx crew took timely action to stay separated from the other aircraft.
联邦快递在五边三英里处时 让西南航起飞是个明智的决定吗?
Was it a wise decision to let Southwest go in front of FedEx while they were on a three mile final?
事后诸葛亮来讲 可能不是
In hindsight, the answer is probably no,
尤其此时交通情况并不拥挤
particularly not at a time of very low traffic
让西南708稍微延误两分钟 一切风险就都没有了
where a short two minute delay for Southwest 708 would've taken all the stress and risk out of the situation.
另一方面来讲 西南航飞行员以其熟练而迅速的起飞闻名
On the other hand, Southwest pilots are known for their proficiency and expeditious takeoffs.
这样的快速起飞在之前数千次的实践中运行良好
Thousands of other times such a takeoff clearance has already worked just fine.
至于最终的责任分配问题 就要看NTSB的全面调查了
When it comes to the ultimate question of responsibility, the full NTSB investigation will decide about that.
今年年初开始 一共报告了8起这样的事故征候
Since the beginning of the year, eight cases of one way incidents have been reported,
其中三起已经被划为B类
three of which have already been classified as Category B.
很难说何时才能确定这是统计上合理的巧合 还是的确暴露一些严重问题
At what point it is no longer a statistically plausible accumulation but a serious problem is difficult to say.
至少某种程度上 当前媒体的关注已经让大家知道了这些多次发生的事件
At least to some degree, the current media attention is highlighting something that has always happened.
这一切都是为了防止历史的重演
All of this is to prevent a repeat of history.
纵观人类航空史最严重的事故排名
If you look at a list of the deadliest aviation accidents that ever happened,
排在第一位的并不是高空坠机 而是两架飞机在跑道上相撞
the number one spot isn't a high altitude crash but rather two planes colliding on the runway.
此次事故发生于1977年 双方为荷兰皇家航空与美国泛美航空
This accident occurred in 1977 between a KLM and a Pan-American flight.
两架飞机都是波音747 当时世界上最大的客机
Both planes were 747s, at the time the largest passenger plane in the world.
驾驶荷航飞机的是该航司经验最丰富的飞行员
In the cockpit of the KLM sits one of the airline's most experienced pilots
甚至曾在公司的广告中登场过
who even appears in the company's advertising.
当时气象条件恶劣 两架飞机看不到对方
The weather had deteriorated massively, and the two planes did not see each other,
塔台管制员也看不到飞机
nor could the tower controller see the aircraft.
当泛美还在跑道上滑行时 荷航已经在跑道头准备起飞了
While the Pan Am is taxiing down the runway, the KLM is lining up for their departure.
飞行员误认为跑道是畅通的 于是决定开始起飞滑跑
And with the pilot under the wrong assumption that the runway is clear, they start rolling.
7年前 当航空公司将波音747投入运营时
When the airlines put the Boeing 747 into service 7 years ago,
核定保险费率的专家预测在投入运营的前18个月会发生两起灾难性的事故
insurance experts trying to set a reasonable rate
predicted 2 disastrous crashes of the huge planes in the first 18 months of service.
两架波音747 曾是世界上最安全的客机
Two 747s, up to now, the world's safest airplane.
昨天 这个安全纪录被它们打破了
Yesterday, the averages caught up with the 747.
两架波音747起初在机场的这一侧 塔台让他们滑行到末端调头起飞
The two 747s were at this side of the field when the tower told him the taxi for takeoff.
泛美航空的机长在浓雾中看到了荷航的着陆灯向他逼近 为时已晚
The Pan Am captain saw the KLM landing lights, bearing at him out of the fog, but it was too late.
损毁的泛美飞机沿着跑道被拖行了约1500英尺
The broken Pan Am plane was dragged about 1,500 feet down the runway.
这是人类航空史上最惨烈的灾难
It was the worst disaster in aviation history.
泛美航空1736号班机 机型波音747
Pan Am Flight 1736, a Boeing 747,
由美国飞往大加那利岛 机上载有380名乘客与16名机组成员
is flying from the United States to the Gran Canaria with 16 crew and 380 passengers.
乘客大多为美国与加拿大公民
The passengers are mostly US and Canadian citizens,
他们将在大加那利岛的拉斯帕尔马斯登上"黄金奥德赛"号邮轮
set to go on a cruise with the MS Golden Odyssey, a ship which they will board at Las Palmas Gran Canaria.
荷兰皇家航空4805号班机 机型同为波音747
KLM 4805, another Boeing 747,
由阿姆斯特丹起飞 同样飞往大加纳利岛
is flying from Amsterdam, also to Gran Canaria,
机上载有235名乘客与14名机组成员
with 14 crew members and 235 passengers on board.
这是一班荷航位荷兰国际旅行集团所开的包机航班
It is a charter flight on behalf of the Holland International Travel Group,
乘客们都是准备去度假的
and the passengers are already looking forward to their vacation.
机长不但经验丰富 拥有11700飞行小时数
The captain is not only an enormously experienced pilot with 11,700 flight hours,
他还是荷航该机型的首席飞行教员
but he is also the airlines chief flight instructor for this type of aircraft.
身为荷航飞行训练部的领导 他有时还会出现在公司的广告中
As the head of KLM flight training department, he's sometimes appeared in the company's advertising.
下午1:15 在荷航抵达大加纳利岛20分钟前
At 1:15 pm, about 20 minutes before the KLM flight is due in Gran Canaria,
机场内一花店发生爆炸
a bomb explodes in a flower shop inside the airport.
炸弹来自加那利群岛独立运动组织
The bomb came from the Canary Islands Independence Movement,
该组织旨在将加那利群岛从西班牙独立出去 依靠暴力来实现他们的目标
a group aiming to break the Canary Islands off from Spain, relying on violence to achieve their goal.
爆炸中8人受伤 索性无人死亡
Eight people were injured by the explosion, fortunately, no one was killed.
在荷航已经开始下降的时候 机场关闭 且开放时间未知
While the KLM is already in its descent, the airport is being closed for an indeterminate time.
机场收到一个威胁电话 声称还有另一枚炸弹
A phone call with the threat of another bomb had been received,
必须找到这颗炸弹 机场才能重新安全开放
and that second bomb still has to be found before the airport can be safely reopened.
荷航因此备降特内里费岛的洛斯罗德奥斯机场
Aeropuerto de Tenerife Norte-Ciudad de La Laguna 特内里费北部机场
旧称Aeropuerto de Los Rodeos 洛斯罗德奥斯机场
The KLM flight therefore diverts to the nearby Tenerife Los Rodeos airport
着陆时间 下午1:48
and lands there at 1:48 PM.
机上235名乘客的假期一开始就延误了
For the 235 passengers on board, their holiday starts with delays
泛美1736是在距离目的地还有一个多小时的时候收到的消息
Pan Am 1736 receives the bad news while they are still more than an hour away from their destination.
机组当时打算减速并进入等待航线
And the crew considers reducing speed and going into a holding pattern to wait out the situation.
但后来他们发现目的地机场一时半会无法重新开放
But when it becomes clear that their destination is not going to reopen anytime soon,
于是在荷航落地一个半小时后也备降在了特内里费
they decide to also divert to Tenerife los Rodeos, and land about half an hour after the KLM flight.
同样备降在特内里费的还有另外三架大型机
Three other large aircraft also divert to Tenerife,
让本来就不大的机场拥挤了起来
and the relatively small airport is now becoming crowded.
此时 机组正在进行备降后的处置工作
At this point, the flight crews are working on contingency plans.
泛美的乘客想要赶紧登上他们的游轮
The Pan Am passengers are expected to check into their cruise ship,
如果没及时赶上 游轮可能就不带他们玩了
and if they don't arrive in time, the ship might leave port without them.
机场的航站楼没有足够停机位停放这些备降的飞机
The airport doesn't have the capacity to park all these incoming planes at the terminal building,
所以荷航停在了滑行道西北方的末端 与跑道方向平行
and so the KLM is parked at the northwestern end of the taxiway that runs parallel to the runway.
大约20分钟后 荷航上的乘客坐摆渡车来到了航站楼
After about 20 minutes, the passengers of the KLM flight are transported by bus to terminal.
泛美的飞机停在了荷航后面 乘客没有下机
The Pan Am flight is parked behind the KLM, but the passengers remain on board.
可能泛美的机组对等待时间的预估比较乐观
Perhaps their flight crew was more optimistic regarding the expected waiting time.
荷航机组考虑到一旦大加纳利岛机场重新开放
The KLM crew anticipates that once Gran Canaria will be reopened,
会有一堆飞机飞过去 到时候排队加油可能会导致进一步的延误
there will be a rush of inbound airplanes, which will cause further delays with services like refuling.
因此他们决定在特内里费岛等待的时候就把油加了
They therefore decide to use the waiting time in Tenerife to refuel,
等到了大加纳利岛的时候就能省不少事
which will speed things up once they reach Gran Canaria.
他们下单了55500升的燃料
They order 55,500 liters of fuel,
他们万万没想到 这个决定最后带走了上百条人命
in hindsight, a decision that might have cost many lives.
荷航正在加油的时候 大加纳利岛消息传来 机场重新开放
While they are refuling, the news arrives that Gran Canaria has reopened
每架飞机的机组都开始忙活起来 飞往他们最终的目的地
and all crews are getting ready to finally fly over to their final destination.
泛美航空最先准备好 但他们必须等前面的荷航加完油才能走
Pan Am calls in first, but has to wait for the refueling of the KLM to be completed,
因为滑行道很窄 没法从荷航旁边绕过去
because the taxiway is too narrow to let them safely pass the KLM.
特内里费到大加纳利岛的飞行很短 但并不是一次常规飞行
The flight to Gran Canaria is short, and yet it's everything but a routine flight.
各种不利因素要求机组成员精神高度集中
Various adverse factors ask for the utmost concentration of the flight crews.
首先 机场气象条件正迅速恶化
First of all, the weather is deteriorating quickly,
能见度可能会降低到允许的最低限度以下
and the required minimum visibility might drop below the permitted range.
这会让他们又延误上几个小时
That of course, would mean another delay of possibly several hours,
给乘客带来种种不便
with all the inconveniences for their passengers.
第二个因素是特内里费机场并没有准备好处理大量备降客机
Factor number two is that Tenerife is not prepared to handle the large number of diverting airliners.
滑行道西北方末端停放的飞机阻挡了正常的滑行交通
The parking aircraft at the northwest end of the taxiway blocks the normal traffic flow.
由于大家都想快点飞走
As everyone wants to get out as quickly as possible,
管制员让荷航与泛美两架飞机一起开始滑行
the controller lets the KLM and the Pan Am start taxiing in close sequence.
想让它俩起飞 需要使用跑道的一部分来让它们滑行
To get these planes to take off, part of the runway has to be used to taxi both planes,
这一程序称为跑道上调头
a procedure called back tracking.
空管的意图是让飞机在第三个脱离道上调头脱离
The intent of the air traffic controller is to let the planes back track on the runway
until reaching the third intersection,
脱离后继续沿滑行道滑行至跑道30外等
when they would exit, and continue on the taxiway until reaching the holding position for runway 30.
管制员让飞机在那排队挨个起飞
From there, he will then let them take off, one after another.
然后荷航呼叫 询问使用哪个脱离道离开跑道
Then when the KLM calls in and inquiries about which intersection they should use to exit the runway,
管制员调整了他的计划
the controller revises his original plan.
管制员优化了他的原始计划
The controller try to optimize his original plan,
让荷航沿着整条跑道滑行至末端调头
and now has the KLM backtrack over the full length of the runway to the opposite end,
而泛美继续按原路线滑行 在第三个脱离道脱离
while Pan Am is still on their original taxi route and supposed to exit the runway at the third intersection.
两架飞机谁走错路线都会出岔子
If any of these two aircraft makes a mistake, chaos is going to happen.
不过目前 一切都还按照计划进行
But still, everything is running according to plan.
但现在气象条件开始恶化
But now the weather is getting worse.
低云飘过机场 能见度降低
Low clouds are moving across the runway and reduce visibility.
泛美的机组开始难以辨认哪个才是第三脱离道
The flight crew of the Pan Am is having difficulty to identify the third exit
只能降低滑行速度防止错过出口
and has to slow down their taxi to not miss it.
两架飞机这时都无法看到对方
Both aircraft can no longer see each other,
空管与塔台也看不见这两架飞机
and the air traffic controller and tower can't see the aircraft either.
此时 荷航的飞机已经快到跑道头 但还未收到空中交通管制许可
At this point, the KLM has almost reached the runway end and not yet received their route clearance,
通常简称ATC许可
sometimes simply called the ATC clearance.
当荷航已接近跑道头 开始180度调转方向时
While the KLM is almost at the end of the runway
and doing the 180 degree turn to face in the opposite direction,
泛美还在跑道上慢速滑行 寻找管制员口中的C3脱离道
Pan Am is still taxiing slowly along the runway, looking for Charlie 3 where they are instructed to exit.
这个脱离道需要飞机进行一个148度的锐角转弯
This exit would require them to do a sharp 148-degree turn.
对于波音747来说并不容易
Not easy, if at all possible with a 747.
飞行员于是在无线电上询问:
The pilots then ask on radio frequency.
当泛美准备在跑道上调头转弯的时候 荷航已经准备好出发了
While the Pan Am is still backtracking on the runway, the KLM is almost ready to go.
此时 机长向前推了一把油门
At this point, the captain advances the throttles,
然后副驾提醒他自己还未收到ATC许可
until the first officer reminds him that they have not yet received their ATC clearance.
管制员给出的许可给出了起飞后的飞行路线
This clearance by the controller instructs the crew of the route they are going to take after takeoff.
但这并不是起飞许可
It is NOT a take-off clearance.
随后 负责与空管通讯的副驾复诵了ATC的许可 并补充道:
Then the first officer who is handling communications with air traffic control
reads the clarence back, and then he adds:
一秒后 机长松开了刹车
Just a second later, the captain releases the brakes
向前推动油门杆 在未获得起飞许可的情况下开始了起飞滑跑
and pushes the thrust levers forward to commence the take-off run,
without having received the necessary take-off clearance.
机组为何没有等待这个必要的许可 目前还不清楚
As to why the crew didn't wait for this required clearance is unclear.
可能他们没意识到自己仍需起飞许可
Perhaps they were not aware that they still needed it.
他们可能听到"起飞后右转"后 以为这就是起飞许可
They might have interpreted the phrase "right turn after take-off" as an implicit take-off clearance.
另外 他们如何确定泛美已经离开了跑道?
And still, how could they be certain that the Pan Am had exited the runway?
荷航最后的回复:
Their response
被进近管制员理解为他们已到达起飞位置 随时准备好起飞
was interpreted by the approach controller
to only mean that they are now at take-off position, ready, but holding still.
但荷航机组的意思是他们就要起飞了
But what the KLM crew meant was that they are about to take off.
进近管制员过了8秒后回复道:
The approach controller answers 8 seconds later:
这句话可能让荷航机组更加肯定了他们可以起飞
which might have reinforced the KLM crew that they were good to go.
然后 两秒后 进近管制员补充道:
Then 2 seconds later, the approach controller adds:
这句话显然会提醒荷航机组中断起飞滑跑
This would normally have alerted the KLM crew to abort their take-off run,
但很可惜 他们那天并没有听到这个消息
but unfortunately, that day, they never heard this message.
原因是 当时有两个发射机在同时讲话 通讯受到干扰
This is due to interference in the radio by two stations transmitting simultaneously.
在进近管制员下达他的指令的时候
At the same time, as the approach controller transmitted his message,
泛美机组好像意识到要出大问题了:
the Pan Am crew became aware that something is going awfully wrong:
无线电中这两句话叠加 在荷航那边听到的只是高频的噪音
The two overlapping transmission cause a shrill noise in the radios of the KLM,
导致两边的话他们都没听到
and they apparently missed the transmission of both.
距离灾难发生还有30秒
Disaster is a mere 30 s away.
进近管制员随后回复泛美机组:
The approach controller then replies to the Pan Am call:
后来在荷航的驾驶舱语音记录仪中是能听到这两段对话的
According to the voice recorder of the KLM, both these transmissions were audible in the KLM cockpit,
随后驾驶舱中出现如下对话:
whereupon the following exchange took place:
飞行工程师的担忧并不是多余的
The flight engineer's concerns are valid,
因为此时泛美仍在跑道中间
because the Pan Am plane is still in the middle of the runway at this point.
可惜 机长并没有重新考虑工程师的想法
Unfortunately, the captain doesn't take the comment as an opportunity to reconsider his decision,
飞行工程师也没再坚持确认跑道是否畅通
nor does the flight engineer insist on making sure the runway is clear.
飞机继续起飞
The plane continues its takeoff.
15秒后 荷航4805撞上泛美1736
15 seconds later, KLM 4805 crashes into Pan Am 1736.
在最后的时刻 双方机组都在尽全力避免碰撞
In the last moment's reaction, both crews tried to avoid the collision,
荷航机组尽全力拉杆让飞机离地
the KLM by prematurely pulling the airplane off the ground,
泛美机组则加速让飞机脱离跑道
and the Pan Am by trying to hurry off the runway.
但荷航并没有来到足够的高度
But the KLM doesn't gain enough height,
它的左侧发动机 下层机舱与起落架撞毁了泛美的上部机身
and its left side engines, lower fuselage and landing gear
plow through the upper section of the Pan Am's fuselage.
荷航的左翼切断了泛美的尾翼
The KLM's left wing then cuts off the Pan Am's tail section.
在两机相撞150米后 荷航撞地
About 150 meters past the crash site, the KLM hits the ground,
它早先装载的大量燃油让自己变成一片火海
bursting into flames, its fuel tanks contributing to the inferno that follows.
荷航上的乘客与机组全部遇难
None of the KLM passengers or crew survived the crash.
泛美航空受到撞击沿跑道滑行了几米
The Pan Am slides a few more meters towards the side of the runway.
乘客与机组共70人逃离了起火的飞机
70 passengers and crew managed to escape the burning aircraft,
他们多数爬上了左侧的机翼
most of them by climbing over the left wing,
但其中9人伤重身亡
but nine of those die later of their injuries.
泛美航空最后只有61人幸存
荷航机上原有一名乘客因住在特内里费岛
趁飞机让旅客下机休息时直接回家了 没有再次登机
Only 61 passengers of the Pan Am flight survive,
本次事故共造成583人遇难
583 lives are lost in this tragic accident.
两架波音747 迄今为止全世界最安全的飞机
Two 747s, up to now, the world's safest airplane.
没有机械故障 悲剧就这样在地面上发生了
Nothing wrong with the mechanically, and then disaster on the ground.
荷航为什么要起飞?
Why did KLM start its takeoff?
真相可能就隐藏在语音记录器中
It hinges on finding their voice recorder.
这样简单的误会 本不该发生
A simple misunderstanding that should never happen.
调查报告中没有提到的一个可能的促成因素
One possible contributing factor not mentioned in the investigation report
是那天不太寻常的空管席位安排
was the unusual combination of air traffic control positions that day.
在事故发生时 有两位空管员在执勤
At the time of the accident, two air traffic control positions were active.
地面管制指挥所有飞机的滑行
A ground controller directing all taxi movements,
进近管制负责跑道上与机场附近空中的交通情况
and an approach controller responsible for traffic on the runway
and airborne traffic in the vicinity of the airport.
这其中的不寻常之处在于这两个岗位的组合
What is so unusual about this is the combination of these two positions.
因为通常情况下 应该是塔台管制负责所有跑道动态
Normally, there would have been a tower position responsible for all runway movements,
特别是起飞与降落的许可
and particularly takeoffs and landing clearances.
塔台与进近管制的组合才是特内里费这种区域机场的标准配置
A combination of a tower plus approach
would have been the normal configuration at a regional airport like Tenerife,
但进近管制员负责跑道上的情况就是一个相当不常见的情况
but an approach controller being responsible for movements on the runway is a rather untypical situation.
在许多情况下 进近管制员甚至看不到跑道
In many cases, the approach controller does not even have a view of the runway,
坐在机场其他的楼里 眼睛盯着雷达屏幕就行
and sits in a separate building of airport, just working from his radar screen.
这种情况下 进近管制只需要给出飞行路线许可即可
In such situations, the approach controller will only give a route clearance,
飞行员必须通过无线电自行负责协调起飞降落
and pilots must coordinate their takeoffs and landings via radio and in their own responsibility.
而在本例中 进近管制就坐在塔台中
In this case, the approach controller was stationed on the control tower,
且在官方调查报告中 他甚至有时就叫塔台管制员
and in the official investigation protocols, he is even sometimes named as the tower controller.
在这种特别的情况下
Given this unique circumstance,
荷航机组或许会认为自己并不需要起飞许可
it is perhaps possible that the KLM crew thought that no takeoff clearance would be given or necessary,
因为不受管制的空域都是这样运作的
as this is how things are normally run on uncontrolled airfields.
但即使这样讲 机组也有责任去证实泛美的飞机已经离开跑道
But even in this scenario, the crew would have had full responsibility
of ascertaining that the Pan Am aircraft was clear off the runway.
他们出发的急切 让他们草草相信了自己的假设
In their eagerness to depart, they just assumed.
官方的调查报告将多数责任归咎于荷航机组
The official investigations put the majority of the blame onto the crew of KLM.
不过也的确还有很多出问题的地方
Although it's acknowledged that many other things had gone wrong.
民航从这次事故中吸取了无数教训
Countless lessons were learned from this accident,
并对程序与规章进行了大量修改
and various changes have been made in procedures and regulations.
事故发生后 所有主要机场都安装了地面雷达
Following the accident, ground radar has been introduced on all major airports,
航空通话用语也有所修改
and aviation phrases have been changed
"起飞"一词只用于管制员下发或撤销起飞许可
to allow the word "takeoff" to only be used in a controller's takeoff clearance,
or when canceling such a clearance.
在其余所有通话中 改为使用"离场"
In all other transmissions, the word "departure" is now used.
航空通话用语全部由各地航空局标准化
Phraseology in general, has been standardized by the aviation authorities.
重要的空中交通指令必须由飞行员复诵
An important air traffic instructions must now be read back by the pilot
以表明自己已完全理解该消息
to acknowledge that they have fully understood them.
"好""收到"等口语词不可作为重要指令的抄收依据
Colloquial replies like OK or Roger are no longer permitted as an acknowledgment of an important transmission.
还有一些措施保证了驾驶舱内一些顾虑的声音能够顺利提出
Steps have also been taken to ensure that concerns inside the cockpit can be raised,
哪怕这些声音会顶撞机长
even if they contradict the captain.
荷航飞行工程师面对经验丰富的机长时内心的顾虑
Some concerns expressed at the experience of the flight captain
可能导致了他没有继续坚持检查跑道是否清空
may have contributed to the fact that the flight engineer
did not further insist on checking whether the runway really was clear.
因此 引入了"机组资源管理"这一全新领域的培训制度
A whole new field of training regime called crew resource management has been introduced,
改善了驾驶舱内的沟通和决策过程
improving the interpersonal communications and decision making processes in the cockpit
并让低级别机组成员的意见得到更多重视
and giving the opinions of lower rank crew members more weight.
这些改进使航空旅行变得更加安全
Improvements like this have made air travel significantly safer,
虽然有时 这些改进是用无数生命换来的
lessons that, unfortunately, have to be learned the hard way.